なんば　むった
＜日本の宇宙開発の中心➡
The center of Japanese space development,
独立行政法人
宇宙航空研究開発機構➡
the Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency.
ジャクサ
ＪＡＸＡ！＞
JAXA.
＜晴れて筆記試験を合格した私
南波六太３１歳は➡
After passing the written test,
I, Nanba Mutta, age 31,
宇宙飛行士となるべく
厳し～い試験と➡
am currently undergoing a brutal exam.
検査を続けているのです＞
Wait... Really?
え…マジで？
Yes, really.
(検査員)ええ マジです｡
パン…ツも？
Even my underwear?
(検査員)パンツも脱いで下さい｡
Please remove your underwear, as well.
《これがウワサの診察か…》
So this is the infamous medical exam...
あの…みんな こんな検査を？
当然です｡
Say, does everyone undergo this exam?
Of course.
女性も？
もちろん｡
Even the women?
Naturally.
《マジかよ ＪＡＸＡめ…》
Really? Damn JAXA...
(せりか)ウフフ…｡
Nanba...
(検査員)南波さん
言っときますが➡
Let me advise you.
今 変なこと考えないようにね｡
Please try not to let your mind stray.
あっ ハイ…｡
Y-Y-Yes...
That was close...
《あぶね～》
《後で考えよう…》
I'll save it for later.
＜宇宙飛行士となるべく➡
I still have many grueling tests
厳し～い試験と
検査を続けているのです＞
and other exams to pass before I can become an astronaut.
ウグッ…｡
Space Brothers
Ah
This feels so good, different from usual
I have no idea what's going on
It feels so good
I never understand what's going on around me
Nothing makes sense to me
Full of questions
Feel so moon
I danced with you in a desert lit by the moon
I won't lose to the rabbit and fly high
I'll fly high
#03 The Man with the Advantage
and the Running Female Doctor
＜むか～し骨折した古傷の
わずかな痕跡から➡
From the tiniest trace of an ancient fracture in my arm,
天パに潜む
小さな枝毛に至るまで➡
to a split end in the curly hair on my head.
とにかく全身
くまなく検査された＞
They examined everything about me.
＜３日目にいたっては➡
By the third day,
体中の穴という穴に
管を通され➡
it felt like they'd stuck tubes in every orifice,
自分でも
見た事のないようなところまで➡
and studied places in my body even I had never seen before.
のぞ
他人に覗かれてしまったのだ＞
A single word came to mind...
《脳裏に浮かぶ単語は二文字》
くつじょく
《｢屈｣と｢辱｣》
Humiliation!
Okay, so today,
(係員)は～い
それでは 今日はですね➡
運動負荷試験ですね｡➡
we'll conduct cardiopulmonary stress tests.
We'd like to assess the strength of your hearts.
皆さんの心肺機能を
見ていきたいと思います｡➡
自分の限界まで走って下さい｡
Please run until you're spent.
(高木)ダメだ こりゃあ｡
I can't take any more...
高木さん ４分３２秒
仲本さん ５分５０秒｡
Takagi. Four minutes, thirty-two seconds.
Nakamoto. Five minutes, fifty seconds.
ハァ ハァ ハァ…｡
ととっ…ハァハァハァ…｡
とととっ…ああっ!!
Good work.
おつかれさま｡南波さんは➡
Nanba, you just ran for eight minutes.
８分ちょうどですね｡
８分!?
Eight minutes?
はっぷん
《やった 八分！
末広がり!!ふふふ…》
All right! Eight minutes...
I'm doing great...
《ダｯシュで８分も走れるなんて➡
((ラモス パース！))
Eight minutes of hard running.
Pass, Ramos!
俺の心肺機能は
あの頃のままじゃないか！》
My heart is still as strong as ever!
おつかれ ムッ君｡
Well done, Mu.
やあ ケンジ｡
ハハハ 君は何分走れた？
H-Hey, Kenji...
How many minutes did you last?
いや～体力落ちてて
全然ダメだよ｡１２分｡
Not too many... I'm completely out of shape.
Twelve minutes.
えっ！やるじゃないか…｡
Not too shabby.
Really?
そう？上には上がいるよ｡
I'm nowhere near the top.
彼らは まだ２０代で
体力もあるらしい｡
Those guys are still in their twenties. And in decent shape.
沢木さん
１５分３１秒です｡
Sawaki. Fifteen minutes, thirty-one seconds.
(溝口)ハァ ハァ…｡
はい 溝口さん
１６分２２秒｡
Okay, Mizoguchi. Sixteen minutes, twenty-two seconds.
なんか ムッ君のこと見てるね｡
Huh?
They're looking at you, Mu.
えっ 俺？
Huh? Me?
＜誰もが驚いた＞
Everyone in the room was stunned.
The one who ran longest,
＜この日 誰よりも長く
１８分間で➡
six kilometers in eighteen minutes...
距離にして６キロ走ったのは
彼女だった＞
It was her.
＜伊東せりかさん｡
女医さんらしい＞
Itou Serika,
a doctor.
《走ってる女性って いいよね》
I like watching a woman run...
(ケンジ)ジャパン
エアロスペース➡
Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency...
エクスプロレーション
エージェンシー➡
で ＪＡＸＡ｡
正解！
Hence, JAXA.
Correct!
そんなの基本すぎるよ ムッ君｡
他の問題！
That's common knowledge, Mu.
Ask me another question.
Th-Then...
じゃ じゃあ…
ＪＡＸＡの職員数は？
How many does JAXA employ?
２５４９人！
Two thousand, five hundred, forty-nine.
や やるね～｡
N-Not bad...
What was the previous former administrator's hobby?
じゃあ ここの
前･前･理事長の趣味は何？
《そんなの 俺も知らね～けど…》
Hell if I know.
(ケンジ)ああ 太田さんね｡
Oh, Oota?
Huh?
２８年間も衛星の設計に
携わってたのに➡
He spent twenty-eight years designing satellites.
But at home, he spent his time on model trains.
家では
鉄道模型が趣味なんだよね｡
しかも Ｍ２５０とかの
貨物車専門｡
And he only built freight trains, like the M250 series.
Correct.
正解！
《コイツ 俺より勉強してやがる》
He's studied more than I have.
(溝口)初めまして 南波さん｡
Nice to meet you, Nanba.
溝口と申します｡
沢木です｡
My name's Mizoguchi.
I'm Sawaki.
Oh.
Those younger men who can really run.
《走れる若者組だ…》
(溝口)噂になってますよ｡➡
Everyone's talking about you.
You're the astronaut Nanba Hibito's older brother?
ひびと
あの南波日々人飛行士の
お兄さんだって｡
Yeah, I guess...
いやあ～まあね｡
That gives you an edge.
有利ですね｡
Eh?
I'm envious.
(溝口)うらやましいですよ｡
日々人さんに➡
Hibito can tell you everything you'll need to know.
全部 教えてもらえる
立場ですもんねぇ｡
今回の試験内容も この先
数ある面接での対応の仕方も➡
The written exam questions,
the best way to handle the interview...
さらには非公開の
三次試験の細部まで➡
Maybe he even told you about the secret third exam,
もう教わってて すでに予習が
できてるんじゃないですか？
so you could prepare ahead of time?
《しっ…しっ…しっ…➡
Sh-Sh-Sh...
しまった～っ!!
その手があったんだ！》
Shit!
I should have asked him...
とか言っちゃってね｡
Just kidding...
I'm just pulling your leg.
冗談ですよ 冗談｡スミマセン
いきなり変なこと言って｡
Sorry for that.
Oh, it's okay.
いや 別に｡
Well, let's all do our best to pass.
(溝口)まあ お互い合格目指して
頑張りましょう｡
《な…なんだ この
チクチクした気持ちは…!?》
Why am I feeling so irritated now?!
ムッ君 気にしちゃダメだよ｡
試験は結局➡
Mu, don't let them get to you.
For this evaluation, what matters is your own ability.
自分の力次第なんだから｡
Oh, yeah.
Damn it. Don't think about it...
《あ～ヤバい…考えるな！》
My hair's gonna start to split again.
《また毛先が分裂するぞ…
チクショー！》
Damn!
《きっと
ここにいる みんなは➡
Everyone here
私が日々人に
試験の内容を教わってて➡
believes I have an edge because Hibito told me what would be on the test.
一番 有利だとか
思ってるんだ！》
《ええい やめろっ！考えるなっ》
No, stop. Don't think about it!
《そして そんな｢有利な私｣を
倒すために彼らは➡
And so,
they must have studied hard,
and trained hard,
きっと私より
何倍も猛勉強し 体を鍛え➡
and prepared hard,
all to beat me!
準備をととのえて来てるに
違いない！》
Which means you might say...
《ってことは ある意味…➡
I'm at a huge disadvantage!
俺が一番 不利じゃん！》
ハァ ハァ ハァ…｡
《今のところ
ケンジにも若手組にも➡
So far,
I've finished behind Kenji and the younger kids in every category.
何ひとつ勝てていない｡
このままじゃ落とされる！》
At this rate, I'm gonna fail.
《全部 一番に
なるぐらいじゃないと…》
To make it, I'd have to win every remaining category.
Wh-What should I do?
ど どうしよう…｡
あ ムッ君｡行くよ！
Mu, let's go.
Huh?
次は肺活量の測定だって｡
Next up is the lung capacity test.
What?
えっ？肺活量!?
L-Lung capacity?
(女医)６０秒経過｡
Sixty seconds.
ぶはっ！
(女医)７５秒経過｡➡
Seventy-five seconds.
最長記録は１１２秒よ｡
頑張って｡
The record is one hundred, twelve seconds.
Hang in there!
ぷはっ！ゲホ…｡
(女医)９０秒経過｡
Ninety seconds.
ブハッ！ハァハァ…｡
プハッ！
あ～しんどっ!!
That hurts!
すごいなぁ まだもってる｡
(仲本)若いからねぇ｡
Impressive. He's still going.
Well, he is still young...
ハァ…どうだ！ヘヘッ…｡
How's that?
Huh?
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)はい｡そう
ここ 六太 伸ばして｡➡
That's it.
Now hold that note, Mutta.
そう｡そうそう…｡
Yes... Like that.
《ず ずいぶん伸びるのね…》
Y-You really can hold that note.
(南波日々人)《長っげぇ～》
That's a long note...
I can keep going...
《もうちょい いける！》
現在
《も もうちょい…いける！》
I-I can keep going!
《なんて すごい人だ…》
She's amazing...
すげえ…｡
Wow...
ひゃあっ！
ホームズとワトソン君で言ったら
ワトソン君だよ｡
I'm more Watson than Sherlock Holmes.
More Robin than Batman...
バットマンとロビンで言ったら
ロビンの方だよ 俺は｡
ハァ…主役にはなれないんだよ｡
I'll never be the headliner.
The best I'll ever get is second place.
俺は最高でも
２位に終わる宿命なのさ｡
ガチャピンとムックで言ったら…｡
More Mukku than Gachapin...
気にすることないよ ムッ君｡
この審査じゃ➡
You shouldn't worry so much, Mu.
They want people who test above average across the board.
１位になることより
平均的に 水準を超えた能力が➡
Not people who only excel in certain areas.
あるかってことを
見られていると思うよ｡➡
それに例えば 身体能力的に
ダントツ１位の人でも➡
For example,
if someone who excelled at every physical exam had mental issues,
they wouldn't be selected.
精神的に問題があれば
不採用じゃないかな｡
ケ ケンジ…｡
K-Kenji...
You really know how to cheer me up, man...
《いいこと言ってくれるぜ
コノヤロウ！》
Right... There's also the mental component.
そっかぁ～精神面か～｡
《しかし俺は…》
Except...
I'm utterly devoid of mental toughness!
《その精神面が 一番自信ない！》
《遠い宇宙が…
さらに遠のいていく》
The long trek to outer space...
grows longer by the minute.
俺が これを着ることは
ないのかな｡
Will I ever get to wear this suit?
《せめて せめて顔を映せば
着てるっぽく…》
Maybe...
Maybe if I see my reflection in the helmet,
it'll look like I'm in the suit.
《見えないね…小っちゃくって》
Or not.
I'm too small.
《うわぁ～！み 見られた！➡
She saw me!
スゲエ恥ずかしい場面を見られた｡
しかも 伊東せりかさんに！》
I totally just embarrassed myself
in front of Itou Serika!
《これで俺はもう 変人決定だ…》
She definitely thinks I'm a weirdo now...
うふっ｡
Oh, there she is.
あ～いたいた｡せりかちゃ～ん
一緒にホテル帰ろう｡➡
Serika!
Let's go back to the hotel together.
シャトルバス出ちゃうよ｡
あ は～い！
The shuttle's about to leave.
Okay!
I'll just take the next bus.
《俺は 次のバスで帰ろう｡
４０分もあるけど》
But that means a forty-minute wait...
《あの人…》
He was...
(ケンジ)じゃ また明日！
Well, see you tomorrow.
おつかれ ムッ君｡
お～う！みなさん おやすみ～｡
It was a long day, Mu.
Yeah.
Good night, everyone!
はあ～あ｡
くも
《10月29日晴れ｡たまに曇り｡
二次試験５日目終了》
"October 29th, sunny...
With a few clouds.
The second exam's fifth day is over."
Tuesday, October 29th
Second exam, day 5, complete.
Treadmill; lung capacity; weight-lifting.
I'm exhausted after all those tests today.
"I'm exhausted after all those tests today."
しんさ
《今日の審査はつか
いろいろやって疲れた｡➡
"Today's lunch!
本日のお昼ごはん！
ＪＡＸＡの食堂にて➡
At the JAXA cafeteria.
A large serving of rice, miso soup, tomato juice,
ごはん(大)
みそしる
味噌汁･トマトジュース➡
and one loaded plate, from the all-you-can-eat salad bar.
一皿のみ取り放題のサラダバーを
てんこもり｡➡
The salad's contents...
サラダの内容｡豆４種の
おから和えを底にしきつめ➡
A base of four types of beans packed together,
followed by lettuce, tomatoes, cucumber, and burdock,
上には レタス･トマト
キュウリ･ゴボウ➡
as well as all the broccoli I could fit.
さらに ブロッコリーを
積めるだけ積んだら➡
Until my salad resembled a giant tree!"
でっかい木みたいになった》
なか
｢お腹いっぱい｣…と｡
"It was so filling."
明日はラーメンにしよ｡
Tomorrow, I'll have ramen.
あっ もしもし お母さん？
H-Hello? Mom?
うん 今日も無事終わったよ｡
疲れた｡あ 今ホテル｡
Yeah, I survived another day...
But I'm so tired.
Yes, in my hotel room.
Today, I saw something amazing!
今日ね スゴイ人見たよお母さん！
あれ覚えてる？
Do you happen to remember
昔 お父さんとＪＡＸＡの
公開イベントに行ったときさ…｡
when we attended the JAXA open house with Dad?
Uh-huh.
そうそう あの時 お父さん｡
That was when Dad...
W-Wait, dear...
((ちょ ちょっとお父さん！
何やってんの？))
What are you doing?
(せりか父)((いや こうすればさ➡
Well, if I do this,
自分が宇宙飛行士に
見えるんじゃないかって))
maybe it'll look like I'm an astronaut.
((恥ずかしいからやめて))
Stop, you're embarrassing us!
アハハハ！そう！思い出した？
That was it...
Do you remember now?
I never thought I'd ever see anyone else do that...
あれと同じこと
やってる人がいたの！
あんなことする人 お父さん以外で
いるんだって思って｡
Anyone other than Dad, that is.
[TV]ワンツー！ワンツー！
は～い 体勢キープ！
One, two.
One... Two.
Now, keep your body straight!
Oh, I see.
((宇宙飛行士みたいに見えた？
お父さん))
So do you look like an astronaut,
Dad?
((ふふふ 教えない))
I can't tell you.
((大きくなったら
せりかもやってごらん))
When you're older, you'll have to try it for yourself.
((うん))
《明日こっそり
やってみようかな》
Tomorrow, when no one's around, I'll give it a try.
《今日の一大ニュース｡➡
"Today's headline.
I saw someone press himself against the spacesuit display.
宇宙服の展示ボックスに
へばりついている人を目撃した｡➡
He looked suspicious...
なんだか怪しげな人だったけど➡
お父さんに会えた気がした｡
うれ
嬉しかった》
But he reminded me of Dad.
So I was happy..."
((ムッちゃん ムッちゃん！
ＪＡＸＡ見えるかな？))
Mu, Mu...
Can we see JAXA yet?
((まだ見えるわけないだろ｡
お前 はしゃぎすぎ…))
((ねえねえ 僕も外見る))
You won't be able to see it yet.
Seriously, calm down.
Hey, I wanna look outside!
くつ
((じゃあ 靴脱ぎなさい ほら))
Then take your shoes off.
Here.
((日々人 お前も靴脱げよ))
Hibito, you should take your shoes off, too...
((ムッちゃん！見て見て！
ロケット!!))
Mu! Look!
A rocket!
Huh? Where?
Look! Over there!
(日々人･六太)うわぁ～！
Oh...
L-Like I said, we can't see anything yet.
((だから 見えねぇって
言ったじゃん！))
(日々人･六太)((ハァハァ…))
Whoa...
(六太･日々人)((スゲエ～！))
Awesome!
Hibito!
Hey!
Huh?
((なんで横から撮るんだよ))
Why did you take the picture from the side?
((だって ムッちゃんのかっこが➡
Because it's hilarious
顔よりお尻の方が飛び出てて
面白いんだもん))
the way your butt sticks out farther than your face...
Mu! Take a picture!
((ムッちゃん 撮ってよ！))
Okay...
Hey, did you take the picture?
((ねえ ちゃんと撮れた？))
おい日々人～ズボン脱ぐな～！
Hey, Hibito!
Don't take my pants off...
ふわ～あ～｡
あと２日！頑張ろう ムッ君｡
Two more days.
Let's do this, Mu.
あくしゅ
何回 握手すんだ 俺ら…｡
How many times are we going to shake hands?
あ…へへ｡
What is it?
(ケンジ)どうしたの？
Why do I feel so embarrassed now?
《なんで俺が
恥ずかしがってんだ？》
え～みなさん それでは
今日のスケジュールを説明します｡
Now, then.
I'll go over today's schedule.
よろしいですか？
《いよいよ この二次審査も➡
Listen carefully.
The second exam will
And please hold your questions until I'm finished.
あと２日で終わる｡ある意味
私が一番 不利かもしれない》
end in two days.
Most likely,
I really am a long shot to make the selection.
But that doesn't matter...
《だとしても 俺は
宇宙へ行きたい！》
I want
to go to space!
The stars I admired were too bright for me
so I quietly closed my eyes
I have faith in you, as you stand alone, full of doubts
I'm right here, next to you
Come now, take my hand and hold it tight
If you do, we will always
have hope, shine with light
and overcome whatever we might face
Do you see how wonderful this world is
and how our future unfolds?
Even the tears we shed and could not put into words
will one day dry up, I am sure
One by one the smiles spread
and ascend towards the starlit sky
(ケンジ)＜ムッ君｡
宇宙飛行士の写真が並んでるよ＞
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#04 Next to Hibito
Mu,
there are pictures of astronauts on the wall.
＜おぉ～ 向井さん！土井さん！
野口さんに 若田さん！＞
Oh, that's Mukai!
Doi!
Noguchi and Wakata!
＜それに 弟 日々人＞
And there's your little brother, Hibito.
There's still plenty of room next to him.
＜まだ 空いてるみたいだな
お前の隣＞
＜ここは 俺の場所だ！＞
That is my place!
So, how was your interview?
＜で 面接は どうだった？＞
＜俺は まあ いけて…➡
It wasn't very good at all...
…ねえんだ 全然！やっちまった＞
I screwed up.
It's all over for me...
＜確実に落ちた＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
Next to Hibito.
＜さよなら…宇宙＞
Farewell, space...
This Week's Space Photo
パンパカパーン！
今週の宇宙写真で～す｡
This week's space photo!
スッゲエ！
Awesome!